<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Porcelain Games Blog</title>
    <description>Porcelain Games is a small indie team dedicated to making elegant, high-quality games. Check out our debut game, &lt;a href=&#39;http://play-impulse.com&#39;&gt;Impulse&lt;/a&gt;
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 00:46:30 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 00:46:30 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First Experience With Feedback Friday</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Feedback Friday is a weekly thread on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/gamedev&quot;&gt;r/gamedev&lt;/a&gt; subreddit where game developers can post their games for constructive criticism. Yesterday, I submitted &lt;a href=&quot;http://play-impulse.com&quot;&gt;Impulse&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that up to this point, I’d been working on &lt;a href=&quot;http://play-impulse.com&quot;&gt;Impulse&lt;/a&gt; in a bubble while neglecting to playtest or market. It’s a classic mistake. The great thing about forums like Feedback Friday is that they don’t require a prior online presence or fan following of any kind, which made it perfect for chumps like me. I was excited to finally start sharing my game with the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;posting-my-game&quot;&gt;Posting My Game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the description I posted in the thread:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://play-impulse.com/blog/assets/img/impulse_gamedev_desc.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts about writing a good description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Definitely give specific questions you want play-testers to focus on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One thing I would change about my description is positioning my web link more prominently on a separate line and get rid of ‘playable in-browser’. Turns out with Unity Web Player, this isn’t as unique as I thought (my game is in HTML5).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My post was on the short side of the spectrum. Some people included a description of their development team, a recent changelog, controls, or even whole press releases. I went through the thread the following day and found that writing more didn’t seem to help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heres an example of a description I found to be clean and effective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://play-impulse.com/blog/assets/img/pixelia_gamedev_desc.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listing key features is an efficient way to give player a rundown of your game. The contact links on the bottom add legitimacy. I’ll definitely be modeling my post after this one in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last point: I posted my game at 6:00pm in the evening, which means less exposure time. Next time, I’ll be posting at midnight sharp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was tempting to stop here and hope for the best, but that felt like a missed opportunity. The Feedback Friday thread was in ‘contest mode’, meaning posts were always shown in a random order. If I took no further action, I would be relying on random chance to get feedback for my game. I didn’t like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;going-through-the-thread&quot;&gt;Going Through the Thread&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After posting my game, the next thing I did was look for games to playtest. I had a hunch that if I gave good, helpful feedback, developers would be willing to look at my game in return. In essence, the amount of feedback and exposure my game received would be directly tied to the amount of time I put into helping others. It was an idealistic notion. Classic reciprocation. I was curious if it would work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deciding which games to play, I primarily looked at &lt;em&gt;how many comments the game had already received&lt;/em&gt;. I preferred to look at games with little or no feedback. In this way, I gave help to developers who needed it most. I also thought there was a higher chance the developer would help me in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;giving-feedback-to-other-games&quot;&gt;Giving Feedback to Other Games&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There a lot of articles on giving good feedback, so I’ll just offer some tips that I found helpful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the developer instructions.&lt;/strong&gt; Make note of what feedback they’re looking for. Don’t waste your time playing parts of the game that aren’t ready. For one game, the dev asked only for testers with controllers. I missed that and spent five minutes trying to figure out how to play the game with a keyboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give the game a serious chance.&lt;/strong&gt; Aim to spend at least 15 minutes playing each game. If you don’t understand the controls initially, keep trying. If something doesn’t work, try to work around it. If the game, god forbid, turns out to be fun, keep playing it. Developers will appreciate the attention you gave to their game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take detailed notes.&lt;/strong&gt; Parts of the UI you disliked. Controls or gameplay elements that confused you. Level design that frustrated you. It’s all gold to the developer. Remember that in an ideal play-testing scenario, you and the dev would be in the same room, and they would be able to watch your emotions, the mistakes you make, your thinking process, etc. Since this isn’t possible, you’ll have to make up for it by being thorough and attentive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be constructive, not critical.&lt;/strong&gt; Your goal is to help them, not make them feel bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An hour into this process, I realized that I was having fun! Considering that I love playing games and thinking about game design and UX, I guess this isn’t surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;asking-nicely-for-feedback-in-return&quot;&gt;Asking Nicely for Feedback in Return&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each of my responses, I added:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hope this was helpful! If you have some spare time, my game Impulse is also on this thread, and I’d love to get your feedback.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, this is a very beautiful alignment of interests. I’m incentivized to write the highest quality feedback I can, in the hope that the developer I’m helping, out of gratitude, will look at my game carefully in return. Of course, this relies on the assumption that indie game developers are generally nice people, a fact I wholeheartedly believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I didn’t get a response, playing other developers’ games and looking at them critically was a great learning opportunity and a chance to see what other people were doing. This in itself made it all worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-results&quot;&gt;The Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave feedback to four games this first Feedback Friday. One of them was the guy who was only looking for controller testers, and I didn’t ask him for feedback because my reply wasn’t very helpful. To my delight, the other three &lt;em&gt;all got back to me&lt;/em&gt; in one form or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that, probably due to my late submission time, I didn’t receive any other feedback other than from the developers I helped. Had I just stopped after submitting, my game would have received no feedback at all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my first Feedback Friday, I:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Posted my game with a succinct description and specific playtesting questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Played other people’s games and gave them high-quality feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requested feedback in return, and got it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to guess, I would say that most developers stopped at step 1. Do the smart thing, and also include steps 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feedback Friday definitely takes a time commitment, but the best part is that you get what you put in. As a gamer, I love it when things work out that way. I’m looking forward to participating again next Friday. I hope I’ll see you there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2015 19:03:48 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/02/20/using-reddit-gamedev.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/02/20/using-reddit-gamedev.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
